<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached July 17. 1676. in the Cathedral Church of St. Peter in York, before the Right Honourable Sir Francis North, Lord Chief Justice of the Common Pleas; and the Honourable Vere Bertie Esquire, one of the barons of the Exchequer; His Majesties judges of assize for the Northern Circuit By Thomas Cartwright D.D. and Dean of Ripon, chaplain in ordiary to His Majesty.</title>
            <author>Cartwright, Thomas, 1634-1689.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1676</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 60 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 23 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A80874</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C703A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R231183</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99899774</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99899774</idno>
            <idno type="VID">136912</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A80874)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 136912)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2442:4)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached July 17. 1676. in the Cathedral Church of St. Peter in York, before the Right Honourable Sir Francis North, Lord Chief Justice of the Common Pleas; and the Honourable Vere Bertie Esquire, one of the barons of the Exchequer; His Majesties judges of assize for the Northern Circuit By Thomas Cartwright D.D. and Dean of Ripon, chaplain in ordiary to His Majesty.</title>
                  <author>Cartwright, Thomas, 1634-1689.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 40 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>In the Savoy: printed by Thomas Newcomb; and are to be sold by Richard Lambert, bookseller in York,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1676.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>With a preliminary imprimatur leaf.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: An assize-sermon. Judges 17.6.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Judges XVII, 6 --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <pb facs="tcp:136912:1"/>
            <p>Imprimatur,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>G. Jane, R. P. D. Hen. Epiſc. Lond. à Sacris Dom.</signed>
               <date>Aug. 13. 1676.</date>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:136912:1"/>
            <p>A SERMON Preached <hi>July</hi> 17. 1676. IN THE Cathedral Church of St. <hi>Peter</hi> in <hi>York,</hi> Before the Right Honourable, Sir <hi>FRANCIS NORTH,</hi> Lord Chief Juſtice of the Common PLEAS; And the Honourable, <hi>VERE BERTIE</hi> Eſquire, One of the Barons of the EXCHEQUER; His MAJESTIES JUDGES of Aſſize for the Northern Circuit. BY THOMAS CARTWRIGHT D. D. And DEAN of <hi>Ripon,</hi> Chaplain in Ordinary to His MAJESTY.</p>
            <p>In the <hi>SAVOY:</hi> Printed by <hi>Thomas Newcomb;</hi> and are to be ſold by <hi>Richard Lambert,</hi> Bookſeller in <hi>York.</hi> 1676.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:136912:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:136912:2"/>
            <head>To the Right Worſhipful, Sir EDMUND JENNINGS Knight, High Sheriff of the County of <hi>YORK.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S</hi> I owe you my Thanks for the <hi>Honour</hi> you did me, in thinking me worthy to be imployed in ſo <hi>Publick a Service,</hi> as <hi>that</hi> to which this Diſcourſe relates; ſo I think it would be more than a <hi>Venial Sin</hi> to offer ſuch a violence to Gratitude, as to <hi>decline your Commands</hi> for the Publication of it. I will not therefore uſe any thing which may look like an <hi>Excuſe,</hi> but inſtantly ſhew how inclinable I am to <hi>prefer your Judgment</hi> before my own; and beg leave to <hi>prefix your Name</hi> before that, which the Nature of the <hi>Subject,</hi> no leſs than the Obligations of the <hi>Preacher</hi> have made wholly <hi>yours.</hi> The chief deſign of the <hi>Sermon</hi> was to convince them that heard it, that our greateſt <hi>Secu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:136912:3"/> under Heaven is the Wiſdom of our <hi>Laws,</hi> the vigorous <hi>Execution</hi> whereof, would remove thoſe manifold Miſchiefs, which the <hi>Relaxation</hi> of them hath bred, and will cheriſh among us. Your <hi>Eminent Loyalty</hi> is ſuch, that I have good reaſon to believe you love the <hi>Sermon</hi> for the <hi>Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects ſake;</hi> and if there be not alſo a Power in <hi>your Judgment</hi> to oblige others to have a <hi>good opinion</hi> of it, I ſhall account my ſelf <hi>ſtrong enough</hi> to abide their Cenſures, whilſt I have <hi>you on my ſide;</hi> and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to make my ſelf the more <hi>valu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able</hi> in the World by <hi>your Friendſhip;</hi> with the continuation whereof you can Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour none who puts a greater value upon it, and who is more ſincerely, than I am,</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Ripon, <date>Aug. 7. 1676.</date>
               </dateline>
               <salute>SIR, </salute>
               <signed>Your moſt obliged and humble Servant, THO. CARTWRIGHT.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:136912:3"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>JUDGES 17. 6.</bibl> In thoſe days there was no King in Iſrael, but every man did that which was right in his own eyes.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He firſt and great Reaſon of <hi>Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Laws and Dominion,</hi> is a Previſion that <hi>all men</hi> will not be a <hi>Law unto themſelves,</hi> ſo as to do their Duty for love or fear of God; and therefore though there be <hi>Judgments to come</hi> in the next Life, denounced againſt all Crimes committed in this, yet did God in the very Infancy of the World make an <hi>Edict for Magiſtracy:</hi> ſo that the <hi>Civil Power</hi> doth derive its <hi>Pedigree from Heaven,</hi> and is a part of the Government over Mankind, in which God uſeth the Miniſtry of Angels, and the ſervice of Men; and it hath accordingly in all Ages been found abſolutely <hi>neceſſary</hi> for the preſervation of <hi>Community, Peace</hi> and <hi>Piety,</hi> not to leave perſons to terrours at ſuch a diſtance as are thoſe of Chriſts ſecond coming to judge the World in Righteouſneſs, but to put
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:136912:4"/> the <hi>Sword of Vengeance</hi> into <hi>one Mans hand</hi> here on Earth for the benefit of all; becauſe if Men ſhould be let looſe to their licentious freedom, wickedneſs would increaſe among them even to cruelty; nor would <hi>Good Men</hi> have any better ſecurity than <hi>Lambs</hi> in a Foreſt of many <hi>Wolves,</hi> if there were not ſome <hi>preſent restraints</hi> for ſuch exorbitant Offenders, whom the determents of the <hi>Life to come</hi> could not over-rule into ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection, that they might at leaſt <hi>obey for wrath, if not for Conſcience ſake.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We are like <hi>Children in their Minority,</hi> not fit to be truſted to our own conduct, but to be <hi>ſecured</hi> at the publick charge of our <hi>Superiours,</hi> to whom next under God and his good Angels we are moſt beholding for our ſafety. Our <hi>Breath of our Noſtrils</hi> is not more neceſſary for our <hi>being,</hi> than our <hi>Princes Sovereignty</hi> is to our <hi>well-being;</hi> for were he not armed with Authority to over-power Evil doers, the Purſe-proud-man would oppreſs the Poor, the Crafty circumvent the Simple, the weaker party be continually expoſed to the ſpoil and rapine of the ſtronger, and we proſtituted to the exorbitant Luſt of every tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulent and domineering Spirit who could pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail to lord it over us.</p>
            <p>From hence we may eaſily conclude, That
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:136912:4"/> thoſe <hi>days muſt needs be evil,</hi> wherein the Civil Government is Unhinged, when the ancient and unqueſtionable Sovereignty over any Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple is cut off; of which ſad ſpectacle your Eyes and mine have been deploring Witneſſes. For what <hi>Iſaias</hi> foretold, was fulfilled in theſe days, <hi>The People were oppreſſed every one by another,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſai. 3. 5.</note> 
               <hi>and every one by his Neighbour; the Child did behave himſelf proudly againſt the Ancient, and the Baſe againſt the Honourable:</hi> When there was <hi>No King in Iſrael,</hi> every one was <hi>more than a King</hi> to himſelf, which is the greateſt Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment that can befal a Rebellious People in this World. For better <hi>any one a King,</hi> than <hi>every one a King;</hi> and yet every one is <hi>more than a King,</hi> if he may <hi>do</hi> without controul what is <hi>right in his own Eyes;</hi> and therefore we are the moſt In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grateful Wretches in the World, and fit to be condemned to ſuch <hi>repeated Confuſions,</hi> if we do not bleſs God, both with our Lips and in our Lives, for the <hi>Re-establiſhment of that Regal Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority,</hi> to which we ſo evidently owe the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of our <hi>Order,</hi> our <hi>Peace,</hi> and our <hi>Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion;</hi> and indeed of <hi>every other good thing</hi> which is and ought to be dear unto us.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Moſes</hi> was the <hi>firſt King in Iſrael,</hi> and when he abſented himſelf from the People but for
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:136912:5"/> forty days, they <hi>Calv'd themſelves</hi> a Molten Image, and became ſuch <hi>Beaſtly Idolaters</hi> as to fall down and worſhip it. Their <hi>new faſhion in Religion,</hi> which they took up in his abſence, (as ridiculous as it was) was quickly <hi>followed by the Crowd;</hi> and their <hi>God of Gold</hi> (though but a Calf indeed) did not long want <hi>Worſhippers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>His next immediate Succeſſor was <hi>Joſhua,</hi> and as ſoon as he was dead, <hi>Micha</hi> and his old doat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Mother <hi>made them both Gods and Prieſts;</hi> and from what occaſion theſe abominable Diſorders ſprang, my Text tells you, the true reaſon was, <hi>There was no King in Iſrael,</hi> none to prohibite or puniſh ſuch Prophanations; and ſo bleſs God or blaſpheme him, be of <hi>any</hi> or <hi>no Religion,</hi> come to Church or ſtay at home; follow any Seducer, though never ſo dangerous; embrace any Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, though never ſo damnable; or eſpouſe any Faction, though never ſo deſperate and ſeditious; turn Idolaters, or commit Sacriledge; every Man may do what he liſts, when there is no Publick Magiſtrate to call him to an account for it.</p>
            <p>Thrice more we read in holy Scripture this Burden of the ſame Lamentation repeated, that <hi>There was no King in Iſrael;</hi> and this upon no leſs <hi>occaſions</hi> than <hi>Idolatry and abominable Lusts,</hi> and with no leſs pernicious conſequences and effects than <hi>Diſorder and Diſſolution.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:136912:5"/>
            <p n="1">1. When there was no King in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> who is <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the living Image of God, the <hi>Tribe of Dan</hi> will have a dead Idol, they <hi>break into Micha's Houſe,</hi> rob him of his Prieſt and and conſecrated things; and if you inquire how ſuch <hi>Sacriledge, Idolatry, Felony</hi> and <hi>Burg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lary</hi> could eſcape their deſerved puniſhment? 'Tis fully anſwered, <hi>that there was no King in</hi>
               <note place="margin">Judg. 18. 1</note> 
               <hi>Iſrael,</hi> no <hi>Heir of Reſtraint,</hi> (for ſo the King is called Verſ. 7. of that Chapter) becauſe He by his Inheritance is obliged to curb and reſtrain all headſtrong Impieties, and to caſt up Boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daries againſt ſuch overflowing Iniquities.</p>
            <p n="2">2. At another time we read of an <hi>horrible Rape</hi> committed, a Woman violently and ſhamefully abuſed by the extravagant Luſt of barbarous Ruffians, and the Spirit of God ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders this alſo for the reaſon of that <hi>violent <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleanneſs</hi> of <hi>Gibeah,</hi> That <hi>there was no King in Iſrael.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Laſtly, The <hi>Men of Benjamin</hi> became the bold Champions of <hi>Gibeah's Lewdneſs;</hi> and being fleſh'd with the double ſucceſs of their evil cauſe, they perſiſted in their Villany, till all but ſix hundred were deſtroyed. Theſe <hi>ſurpri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed the Virgins dancing at Shiloth,</hi> raviſh'd them away by violence from their Parents, and <hi>en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forced
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:136912:6"/> them to Marriage;</hi> of which <hi>Rape</hi> and <hi>Riot</hi> the reaſon rendred is the ſame as it was of the former, <hi>In thoſe days there was no King in</hi>
               <note place="margin">Judg. 21. 23, 25.</note> 
               <hi>Iſrael.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So that my Text, you ſee, is no <hi>ſingle in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance,</hi> no <hi>particular, ſtrange, caſual,</hi> or <hi>acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dental Emergence;</hi> but <hi>as it was in the beginning,</hi> ſo it <hi>hath been</hi> ever ſince, and <hi>will be</hi> undoubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edly <hi>to the Worlds end; Where there is no King</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 36. 3. Deut. 33. 5</note> (that is, <hi>no ordinary Judge or Governour,</hi> as the word is elſewhere taken) <hi>every one will do that which is right in his own eyes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>My Text is made up of <hi>Confuſion, Anarchy,</hi> and the <hi>ſad Effects</hi> of it divide it and the World; nor can you expect any <hi>perfect Method</hi> in the proſecution of ſuch Diſorders, wherein we are concerned to take notice of theſe three Parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars:</p>
            <list>
               <item>I. The <hi>Tragical Antecedent,</hi> wherein the <hi>great cauſe of Iſraels Miſeries,</hi> and from what remarkably <hi>fatal time</hi> they bore date, is recorded; <hi>In thoſe days there was no King in Iſrael.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>II. The <hi>Terrible Conſequent,</hi> or <hi>Iſraels</hi> diſmal condition without their King; <hi>Every one did that which was right in their own Eyes.</hi>
               </item>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:136912:6"/>
               <item>III. The <hi>Infallible Connexion between that Cauſe and this Effect;</hi> the one is ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tail'd upon the other, that there is but an intermediate <hi>Comma,</hi> hardly a breathing ſpace, between the loſs of a King and Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centiouſneſs:</item>
            </list>
            <p>Which makes the words by a clear <hi>Epiphonema</hi> to declare the <hi>great Benefit</hi> of a Legitimate King in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> the <hi>Neceſſity of Laws,</hi> and the <hi>Happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> of thoſe People, who live under ſuch a Government as takes an impartial care of their execution, which will bring the Text home from the <hi>Jews</hi> to the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> from thoſe in <hi>Iſrael</hi> to us in <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now the worſt beginning that any Men li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ever made, was, when we of this Nation began to be a weary of our <hi>Late Martyr'd So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vereign,</hi> that being the <hi>fatal time</hi> from whence we may experimentally derive the <hi>Original Cauſe</hi> of all ours, as the Holy Spirit hath here done of <hi>Iſraels</hi> Miſeries; which I therefore term,</p>
            <p n="1">1. The <hi>Tragical Antecedent: In thoſe days there was no King in Iſrael.</hi> After <hi>Sampſon</hi>'s death, there was an <hi>Inter-regnum,</hi> not under <hi>Othoniel,</hi> but between <hi>Sampſon</hi>'s and <hi>Eli</hi>'s Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, (to which <hi>Druſius</hi> and <hi>Tremellius</hi>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:136912:7"/> think this inſtance relates.) Others ſay there was no Supream and continual ordinary Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate over the whole body of the People; for the Judges were extraordinary, raiſed at Gods pleaſure over a part of the People, and without abſolute Authority; and therefore the People<note place="margin">Judg. 2. 17</note> would not hearken unto them, becauſe their Power was only of Direction, not of Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; they could counſel, but not correct them: There were at that time many Task-maſters over <hi>Iſrael,</hi> but no King in it.</p>
            <p>Now the King is of as publick and univerſal Influence in his Dominions, as is the Sun in the Firmament, He being the Publick Ballancer of each Private Intereſt, with which he is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truſted as the proper Guardian of Equity and Juſtice, <hi>Cuſtos utriuſque Tabulae,</hi> to whoſe Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Cuſtody God hath committed the Two Tables of the Law, and intruſted Him to ſee that we live ſoberly among our ſelves, religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly towards God, and righteouſly towards our Neighbours.</p>
            <q>Rerum prima Salus &amp; una Caesar.<note place="margin">Martial l. 8. Epigr. 65.</note>
            </q>
            <p>He is the principal Pillar upon which the Streſs of his Kingdom lies; and as the King doth not live <hi>Sibi, ſed Populo,</hi> ſo neither doth
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:136912:7"/> He die to his own, but to their diſadvantage; and though ten thouſand others might ſteal out of the World and no body mind or miſs them, yet the <hi>Loſs of Him</hi> will be as ſoon felt, as the plucking up of a ſubſtantial Stake out of a rot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten Hedge, or the removal of a Buttreſs from a declining Wall. And when this <hi>Tutelar Angel of a Kingdom</hi> is recall'd, 'tis time for the Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants to tremble, for fear of the <hi>Deſtroying An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel</hi>'s coming among them. A King will be ſuddenly and ſoundly miſs'd, not only in <hi>Edom</hi> but in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> which will quickly turn to a <hi>Babel</hi> without him, in as much as that very Law by which we hold our Lives and Liberties will be but a <hi>Dead Letter,</hi> unleſs it have <hi>his Authority</hi> to actuate and enliven it. For let the Rule be never ſo ſtrait and perfect, it meaſureth nothing out of his Hand who hath skill to uſe it; and when the <hi>Law</hi> hath defined what is Right or Wrong, there will want a <hi>Judge</hi> to ſentence for the <hi>Plaintiff</hi> or <hi>Defendant;</hi> and let the <hi>Directive Power</hi> of the Law be never <hi>ſo good,</hi> it muſt of neceſſity fall to the ground, if there be not <hi>a co-active</hi> to aſſiſt it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Libertas Libertate Perit,</hi> to live as we pleaſe would be the ready way to loſe our Liberty, and undo our ſelves. Tyranny it ſelf were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finitely
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:136912:8"/> more tolerable than ſuch an unbridled Liberty. For that like a <hi>Tempeſt</hi> might throw down here and there a fruitful Tree, but this like a <hi>Deluge</hi> would ſweep away all before it: and <hi>Confuſion</hi> hath ever been found ſo much worſe than the <hi>hardeſt Subjection,</hi> and even the <hi>moſt corrupt Government</hi> ſo much better than a <hi>Civil War,</hi> that it was over-ruled in <hi>Nerva</hi>'s time by <hi>Fronto</hi> the Conſul, <hi>Melius est ſub his</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cardan. Encom. Neron. c. 5</note> 
               <hi>eſſe, ſub quibus nihil licet, quam ſub quibus om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia:</hi> That it is better to live under the <hi>ſevereſt Prince,</hi> where every <hi>Suſpicion</hi> is made a <hi>Crime,</hi> and every Crime <hi>Capital,</hi> than to have <hi>none</hi> at all but a lawleſs Anarchy. And therefore the want of a King of which <hi>Iſrael</hi> ſo much complains, is a <hi>complicated Miſchief,</hi> involving many thouſand Evils in it, and ſuch as are not to be calculated by any ſingle perſon, but we muſt all lay our heads together to ſum them up; which that we may the better do, I proceed to examine that particular account, which the ſecond part of my Text gives of them, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">II. The <hi>Terrible Conſequent,</hi> or <hi>Iſraels</hi> miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable condition without their King, in as much as <hi>every one did that which was right in his own Eyes.</hi> Every Man whoſe ſhort-ſighted Soul can ſee no farther than his Eye, ought not to
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:136912:8"/> be empanneld to give in a Verdict of <hi>Right,</hi> of which to expect a true Judgment from him, were to exact an account beyond the Sphere of his notice. For admit, that ſome of <hi>Nature's Courſer Wares</hi> may lie upon the Bulk, expos'd to the tranſient view of <hi>every Vulgar Eye;</hi> yet theſe her <hi>Choicer Jewels</hi> of Right and Equity are lock'd up in her private Cabinet, for their ſight who can purchaſe them at their due rates of Sweat and Oyl. If therefore <hi>any Mans Eye</hi> be the competent Judge of Right, yet without peradventure <hi>not every Mans;</hi> certainly not thoſe of the <hi>Croud,</hi> who proſtrate their Aſſent to every ſhallow Appearance, and defile their Judgments with each bold Conjecture that flatters them. And indeed if every private Man had <hi>Wit and Honeſty</hi> ſufficient to govern him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf and his own Actions, there would be no need of Publick <hi>Laws</hi> to direct, and <hi>Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates</hi> to guide them: But alas! moſt Mens Minds are too much out of order to have ſuch a Truſt repoſed in them, as being acted by fond and abſurd Principles, and ſo horribly impos'd upon by their Vices and Paſſions, that their De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terminations are as different as their Judgments, and thoſe as their Intereſts; and they who have no reaſon in them but <hi>their Wills,</hi> will hear none
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:136912:9"/> againſt them, which would make Controverſies and Diſſentions endleſs, if the Wiſdom of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence in a foreſight of theſe Miſchiefs to which we are thus obnoxious, had not caus'd us all to be born Subjects to ſome Empire, placing a <hi>Prince and Prieſt</hi> at firſt in every Family, and ſuffering none, ſince the World was better peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pled, to live without the Reſtraints of an over-ruling Government.</p>
            <p>But if <hi>every Mans Eye</hi> could be ſuppoſed to be the competent Judge of <hi>ſome Right,</hi> yet without peradventure not of <hi>his own Right,</hi> for we are prone to fawn upon our ſelves, and to be wilfully ignorant of our own failings. Our <hi>Affections</hi> do ſo eaſily bribe our Judgments to moſt apparent degrees of inequality, that it will be in vain to expect a <hi>Right Sentence</hi> where the <hi>Judge</hi> is a <hi>Party.</hi> We do ſo infinitely believe what makes for our ſelves, and ſo eaſily ſettle in a firm perſwaſion of the goodneſs of our own Cauſes without examining them, that any thing <hi>ſeems Right</hi> to us, if it be <hi>our Interest</hi> to have it ſo; and whatſoever we ſee through thoſe <hi>Selfiſh Spectacles,</hi> comes with ſuch great improvement to our Judgments, that as oft as <hi>Reaſon</hi> is againſt us, ſo oft are we <hi>againſt Reaſon. Rectum non ex propria recti, honeſtique rationem, ſed ex
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:136912:9"/> uniuſcujuſque libidine definitur:</hi> Nor is there <hi>any Crime</hi> ſo bad but it ſeems <hi>as right</hi> in ſome Mens Eyes, as the <hi>Worſhipping of an Idol</hi> did in <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cha</hi>'s, or as <hi>Rebellion under pretence of Religion</hi> did to them who had <hi>Eſpous'd the Good Old Cauſe;</hi> and in pure tenderneſs of Conſcience to make her a <hi>Sufficient Dowry,</hi> Joyntred her in the Blood and Eſtates of their Lawful Sovereign and his Loyal Subjects, till their Goſpel-Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation was in a manner compleated, and the <hi>Godly Party came to Inherit the Fatteſt Portions of this Land.</hi> Nor need we go back to them for an inſtance of Mens being blinded with their Paſſions and Intereſts; for <hi>we</hi> ſee not the <hi>Beams in our own Eyes,</hi> but hug our very De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formities when they bear our Names, and will hardly be perſwaded they are ſo, when we take our ſelves to be their Authors.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Nemo ſuae mentis motus non aeſtimat aequos</l>
               <l>Quodque volunt homines, ſe bene velle putant. <note place="margin">Prov.</note>
               </l>
            </q>
            <p>Many Men, many Minds, and each ſtrongly addicted to his own. If therefore <hi>every Man</hi> ſhould be his <hi>own Judge,</hi> ſo as to take upon him to <hi>determine his own Right,</hi> and according to ſuch Determination to proceed in the mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of it, not only the Government, but the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:136912:10"/> Kingdom it ſelf would quickly come to ruine: and yet admit of the former, and you cannot exclude the latter. For <hi>the Hand</hi> will follow <hi>the Eye,</hi> and Men <hi>do as it ſeems right to them,</hi> be it never ſo wrong in it ſelf: ſo that if a <hi>vicious Eye</hi> be ſeconded with <hi>strong Hands,</hi> and there be <hi>No King</hi> to pinion them; we cannot expect more Miſeries, than will infallibly invade us, nor fewer than befel the <hi>Jews,</hi> when <hi>every Man did that which was right in his own Eyes.</hi> Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes in the <hi>Eye,</hi> Errours in the Judgment, are dangerous; and there being not <hi>one Reaſon in us,</hi> there is the more need of <hi>one Power over us.</hi> Yet they who ſee amiſs, hurt none (they ſay) but themſelves: But how if their unquiet Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions will not be kept at home? but proves as Thorns in their Sides, and will not ſuffer them to take any reſt, till from <hi>Liberty of Thinking,</hi> they come to <hi>Liberty of Acting?</hi> (which the moſt Judicious <hi>Hooker</hi> foreſaw they would do, and we have ſeen they did.) Then without queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, if we cannot pull Mens Eyes out of their Heads, (which were inhumane to attempt) nor beat them out of their perverſe Opinions, (which were unchriſtian) yet at leaſt it is the Publick Intereſt and the Magiſtrates Duty to <hi>pinion their Hands,</hi> and bind them to the Peace;
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:136912:10"/> and the Kings Charge it muſt conſequently be, to look to <hi>His Subjects Eyes,</hi> as well as he can, that they ſin not blindly for want of Direction; and eſpecially to their <hi>Arms,</hi> that they ſin not with a high Hand for want of Correction; to look well to <hi>Micha</hi> in matters of Religion; to take care to pull Falſe Worſhip down, and to ſet up the Power of Godlineſs in its room. The letting looſe of that ſtring of Uniformity, which the Laws have ſcrued up to its juſt pitch, will make greater Diſcords in the Harmony both of Church and State than we can eaſily ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Regis quiſque intra ſe animum habet.</hi> Every Man is apt to take more Liberty than he will allow, and to look upon the Reſtraints of Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority as an Incroachment upon his Birth right; and therefore <hi>doing of Right</hi> is a ſmooth term with them who are for the moſt part <hi>in the Wrong;</hi> and <hi>Liberty of Conſcience</hi> the plauſibleſt thing in the World, even among <hi>Men of no Conſcience at all.</hi> But our <hi>Wiſer Progenitors</hi> who expected Protection, not only <hi>for Themſelves</hi> but <hi>their Posterities,</hi> did and might as reaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably <hi>ingage for our Obedience</hi> to them who ſhould protect us; nor are we therefore <hi>born in a ſtate of abſolute Liberty,</hi> to chuſe what Laws
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:136912:11"/> and Governours we pleaſe; but <hi>Subjects</hi> to that Authority we now live under, which we are bound to preſerve both in Church and State with our Lives and Fortunes.</p>
            <p>Nor is there any reaſon we ſhould be <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, lawleſs, to do what we pleaſe: for we cannot fathom the depth and <hi>deceitfulneſs of our own Hearts,</hi> much leſs of the Hearts of other Men, which are <hi>fruitful in evil, and every day bring forth new Inventions.</hi> Only this we know, <hi>Cui plus licet quam par eſt, plus velit quam licet,</hi> We are all the worſe for that which we miſtake for Liberty, (miſtake I ſay) for to live as we pleaſe, is indeed to <hi>loſe our Liberty,</hi> of which the <hi>Law</hi> is ſo far from being <hi>an Abridgement,</hi> that it is the only <hi>Firm Foundation</hi> upon which it muſt be built, if it ſtand for ever, there being no <hi>True Liberty</hi> but <hi>under ſome Law;</hi> to which when Men fling off their Obedience, they bring themſelves under the <hi>Devils Yoak;</hi> nor is there any thing <hi>more unlike Liberty</hi> than that which they then contend for with ſo much heat and violence. A Liberty to manifeſt our folly and wickedneſs, to be <hi>unjuſt and unholy,</hi> to injure our Brethren and our ſelves, is but a <hi>Licence and Protection for Villany,</hi> which is the greateſt <hi>Sla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very</hi> on this ſide Hell; and yet <hi>a little more</hi> of
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:136912:11"/> this Liberty they would fain have, who have had <hi>too much</hi> already, (unleſs they had uſed it better.) The Croud would fain be let looſe, to do what they pleaſe; which Freedom that they may the better obtain, they are taught (by them who know beſt how to ſet a Rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion on foot) to pretend <hi>Conſcience,</hi> and an <hi>Inward Light</hi> for all their Aims and Actions, how dark and dangerous ſoever; which fond pretence hath in all Ages <hi>bid defiance</hi> to the Swords and Scepters of <hi>Sovereign Princes,</hi> and <hi>Countermanded</hi> the Laws of their Inacting; and whenever the <hi>Rabble</hi> had a mind to Rebel, eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry thing they would have introduced or alter'd in the Government was <hi>their Conſcience,</hi> and their fouleſt Villanies were ready to juſtifie themſelves by <hi>Scripture Authority.</hi> Now by <hi>their Conſciences</hi> (for the <hi>Liberty</hi> whereof this Nation hath unhappily ſpent that Blood and Treaſure which we might have kept for better purpoſes) the modeſteſt of them meant, I think, <hi>their Judgment, and Opinion of their own Actions;</hi> and did accordingly become <hi>Humble Petitioners</hi> to our <hi>Martyr'd KING of Bleſſed Memory,</hi> that <hi>their Dictates</hi> might be certain <hi>Peculiars</hi> exempt from the Juriſdictions of their Sovereigns Decrees.</p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:136912:12"/>
            <p>No Nation under Heaven hath been more over-ſtock'd with ſuch <hi>Libertines</hi> than this of ours, where they have been laying the Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation for above forty years laſt paſt, of the moſt <hi>looſe, uncertain</hi> and <hi>pernicious</hi> Religion in the World. When they hear the Eccho of their own Luſt and Concupiſcence ſpeaking within them, they tell their deluded Admirers, that it is the Voice of the Spirit; and being once <hi>enlighted with ſuch Illuſions,</hi> they bring in God to <hi>Witneſs againſt Himſelf,</hi> and to ſpeak by them <hi>from Heaven</hi> againſt what he hath decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red before by his Son upon Earth; upon which Foundation what a <hi>Babel of Confuſion</hi> hath been erected, and what <hi>foul Sins</hi> have advanc'd them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves upon theſe <hi>ſpecious Principles,</hi> even to the out-facing of all Authority, we have ſadly ſeen and felt too much already.</p>
            <p>Men of <hi>Diſtempered Minds</hi> as well as <hi>Craſie Bodies</hi> being poſſeſſed with a diſcontent and diſlike of things preſent, do naturally imagine that <hi>any thing,</hi> the <hi>Virtue</hi> whereof they hear commended by their Friends, will help them, and <hi>that moſt</hi> which they have tryed leaſt; and therefore they liſten greedily to any <hi>Alterations</hi> of that Government which is uneaſie to their Humours. A <hi>Rent</hi> in the Church they hope
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:136912:12"/> may make up the <hi>Breaches</hi> in their Eſtates and Reputations, and the <hi>Ruines</hi> of the Kingdom <hi>build</hi> up their Fortunes; and therefore no won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der if they deſire to acknowledge <hi>No King in Iſrael</hi> but Chriſt, and <hi>every one to do that which is right in his own Eyes,</hi> without the controul of his Governours, who are intruſted with the <hi>Sword of Juſtice</hi> to repreſs thoſe Armed Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orders which are embowel'd in that <hi>Trojan Horſe,</hi> which theſe <hi>Crafty Sinons</hi> would intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce.</p>
            <q>Hoc Ithacus velit, &amp; magno mercentur Atridae.</q>
            <p>If this be admitted, <hi>King JAMES His Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecy</hi> will be ſoon fulfill'd, <hi>The Pope will be brought into</hi> England <hi>upon the Puritans back:</hi> And though I am ſo <hi>Charitable</hi> as to hope, that they do not in the leaſt deſign it; yet I am alſo <hi>ſo purblind</hi> that I cannot ſee the leaſt danger of his entrance any other way, notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the many Jealouſies of this kind with which we are daily alarm'd.</p>
            <p>But alas, What an <hi>Inſignificant Cypher,</hi> what a meer <hi>Picture of Authority</hi> would a <hi>King</hi> be, if every <hi>private Mans perſwaſion,</hi> which he has learn'd to call his Conſcience, ſhould give <hi>check</hi> to the Magiſtrates Commands? And how im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:136912:13"/> is it for the King to abridge them of <hi>Liberty of Conſcience,</hi> the pleading for which makes ſo great a noiſe in the World? For Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty of Conſcience rightly ſtated, is an Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal and Inviſible thing, ſeated in that part of a Man, of whoſe ſecret Operations, which are but pure Speculations, the <hi>Civil Power</hi> can take no Cognizance. Men may <hi>think</hi> of things ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their own perſwaſions, and aſſert the freedom of their Judgments in their <hi>Intellectual Kingdoms</hi> againſt all the Emperours in the World. Nor is ſuch a <hi>Private Sovereignty</hi> as this any Incroachment on the Prerogatives of Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, becauſe <hi>Meer Opinions</hi> as ſuch, have no in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence upon the Good or Evil of Humane So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cieties, which is the proper Object of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; ſo that if the Opinion be <hi>ſhut up and muzled,</hi> if it dwell quietly at home, and take not the Air to moleſt and endanger others, Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority lays no reſtraint upon it. But when it ſallies out of its own <hi>Sanctuary,</hi> into outward Action, and <hi>invades</hi> the Magiſtrates Territories, till it come from Liberty of Perſwaſion to Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty of Practice, and throws <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſuch <hi>Fiery Darts of Satan</hi> among his Subjects<note place="margin">Eph. 6. 16.</note> as may inflame and wound them, 'tis both his <hi>Duty</hi> and <hi>Intereſt</hi> to have a care of the Publick
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:136912:13"/> Weal, and to put a Bit in the Mouth of ſuch an head-ſtrong and unbridled Liberty as would run full ſpeed into all the Miſchiefs and Enor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities imaginable. God knows the generality of Mens Conſciences are very inſufficient and <hi>incompetent Judges</hi> of their own Actions; and to leave them to the Government of their own <hi>Deluſive Perſwaſions,</hi> were in effect to <hi>deliver them up to Satan,</hi> to be abuſed and tormented with every Luſt, which had debauched their Underſtandings. We have ſeen of late years what a <hi>Croſs-grain'd Thing</hi> this <hi>Liberty of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience</hi> is, how many <hi>Rebels it Armed,</hi> and how many <hi>Drums</hi> it beat up for Reformation, till Humour, Prejudice and Peeviſhneſs prevailed to Murder the <hi>Best of Princes.</hi> Nor can we be reaſonably ſtartled at any greater <hi>Symptoms of the departure</hi> of that <hi>Happy Government</hi> which God hath now bleſſed us with, than every Mans reſolving to be over-ruled by none but his own Perſwaſions; from the growth of which pernicious Deluſion, Good Lord deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver us. For if there were <hi>No King in our Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael,</hi> we ſhould ſoon <hi>feel</hi> by theſe Mens Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons what were <hi>Right in their Eyes,</hi> and be tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowly convinced of the Truth of <hi>the third part of my Text;</hi> viz,</p>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:136912:14"/>
            <p n="3">III. <hi>The Infallible Connexion between that An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tecedent and this Conſequent,</hi> the Loſs of a King and Licentiouſneſs. <hi>In thoſe days there was no King in Iſrael, Quid plus velit ira?</hi> There was no full ſtop to more Miſeries yet; there is but a meer <hi>Comma,</hi> a ſhort breathing ſpace, and it inſtantly follows, <hi>Every Man did that which was right in his own Eyes.</hi> We are not yet grown ſo old in our regained Happineſs, as to have out-worn the ſenſe of our late Diſorders. Thoſe <hi>Fatal Days</hi> are not yet forgot, wherein the <hi>Curſed Regicides</hi> pull'd down <hi>Gods Deputy</hi> to ſet up <hi>Devotion,</hi> defac'd the <hi>Churches</hi> to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troduce a <hi>Form of Godlineſs,</hi> and <hi>grub'd</hi> up the ſoundeſt and ſtraiteſt <hi>Cedars</hi> of it by the Roots, to plant a Grove of crooked hollow hearted <hi>Elders</hi> in their room, till they came to hold the <hi>Laws</hi> themſelves <hi>under Sequeſtration,</hi> as well as the Rights and Revenues of the Crown and Church, and of all ſuch good Subjects and Chriſtians as had Courage and Conſcience enough to defend either. Indeed we can hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly name that Wickedneſs which was not then Tolerated, Countenanced, Encouraged and Applauded, when the <hi>Sword of the Spirit</hi> had once found a new way to the Conſcience, even <hi>by cutting thorow the Fleſh.</hi> From which hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:136912:14"/> 
               <hi>Enormities,</hi> which a <hi>King in Iſrael</hi> would, and when he is Dethron'd, none elſe can, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent and remedy, give me leave by way of Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication to infer three things.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>The Neceſsity of Laws and Governours.</hi> If <hi>all</hi> Men were <hi>Vertuous,</hi> every Man would be <hi>a Law to himſelf;</hi> but there being <hi>very few</hi> who can guide themſelves, and <hi>very many</hi> who will not be guided by others without conſtraint, there is a viſible need both of a <hi>Directive</hi> Power to make Laws, and of a <hi>Coactive</hi> to put them in Execution. The <hi>Law without the King</hi> is but a <hi>Dead Letter,</hi> He is <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the Living Law; and as without Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment there would be no <hi>Communities,</hi> but rather <hi>Herds of Men;</hi> ſo without ſuch <hi>Coercive Power</hi> of his, there could be no Government; and if the <hi>Power</hi> of which the King is poſſeſs'd did not ſo <hi>vaſtly exceed</hi> that of his Subjects who are to obey, that in caſe of a <hi>Conteſt</hi> it would be moſt unreaſonable for them to hope to maintain their Cauſe and Party againſt him, we ſhould never be free from Tumults and Sedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; and therefore Men being more Ruled by Hopes and Fears, than by a ſenſe of Duty and love of Goodneſs, 'tis neceſſary for the <hi>Maintenance of Societies,</hi> not only that it be
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:136912:15"/> declared, <hi>What Men ought to do;</hi> but alſo that the <hi>Penalties</hi> be ſet forth which they ought to ſuffer upon the Violation of thoſe Laws where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon the Society doth ſubſiſt, for which they are to be <hi>accountable</hi> to ſuch who by their Oaths and Offices are bound to ſee the Laws obey'd, and Offenders puniſhed: ſo that although there <hi>be Kings,</hi> yet except they carefully <hi>execute their Laws,</hi> that no Man be ſuffer'd to <hi>do what is right in his own Eyes,</hi> without ſuffering the Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalties impoſed by Law, Diſorder and Diſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution will quickly follow.</p>
            <p>The Laws ought to be of an <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nyielding and Inflexible Temper,</hi> and not ſuch ſoft and eaſie things as to bend to their humour whom they ought to command. Nor do I know any Rule either of <hi>Policy</hi> or <hi>Piety,</hi> whereby the <hi>Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of the Superiour</hi> is bound to relax his Laws, becauſe the <hi>Inferiour</hi> thinks ſo. For if <hi>one Man</hi> can make it neceſſary to change the Law in complyance with his Opinion, then why not <hi>every one?</hi> and ſo no Law ſhall be in force, but what Malefactors have a mind to, and every Man ſhall be bound to pleaſe himſelf in <hi>doing that which is right in his own Eyes,</hi> which is the ready way to Nurſe up Factions and Seditions to a <hi>Grandure ſo formidable,</hi> as to be able when
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:136912:15"/> they ſee their own time to change the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Church and State.</p>
            <p>'Tis <hi>ſometimes neceſſary</hi> for the Publick Weal to puniſh <hi>Well-meaning Perſons</hi> for ſuch Offences into which they have been betrayed through their own Ignorance and Inadvertency, and by the artifice of ſome <hi>Grand Seducers:</hi> but it is <hi>always neceſſary</hi> to puniſh ſuch, who unleſs they <hi>mean better</hi> now than they did be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, mean to <hi>bathe</hi> their <hi>Tender Conſciences</hi> in the Blood of our Gracious Sovereign and their fellow-Subjects; and therefore it is high time for them who are <hi>in Authority,</hi> not only to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider the <hi>preſent,</hi> but to inlarge their Vigilancy for the <hi>times to come;</hi> to permit nothing <hi>now,</hi> which may <hi>hereafter ſhake the Throne of David,</hi> and to beſtir themſelves againſt ſuch <hi>Anti-Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchical,</hi> and <hi>Anti-Epiſcopal Spirits,</hi> as have been <hi>Conjured up</hi> in this Rebellious and Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puting Age, till they <hi>lay</hi> ſuch Infernal Impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors, and <hi>compel</hi> them to that Modeſty and Obedience by the Sword of Juſtice, to which all the Rhetorick and Reaſon in the World can never <hi>court</hi> them. And I know your <hi>Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips</hi> underſtand your ſelves and the preſent Diſtempers of this poor diſtracted Kingdom better than to hope to remove the Diſeaſe by
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:136912:16"/> feeding the Humour. If the Foundations of Faith, Good Life and Government be not ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured by the due execution of the Laws, we ſhall neither have Truth nor Peace long among us: From whence we may infer,</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>The great Benefit of a Legitimate King and his Government,</hi> as of that in which our Strength lies, as did <hi>Sampſons in his Hair;</hi> which if cut off, we ſhould quickly betray our Weakneſs to the <hi>Philiſtines</hi> falling upon us. <hi>Munimentum Gentis eſt Juſtitia;</hi> Juſtice is the Fortification of a Kingdom, and Laws the <hi>Soul of the Body Politick,</hi> by which its parts are <hi>animated</hi> and ſet a work in ſuch Actions as the common good requires, which taught <hi>Plato</hi> to derive their Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digree from Heaven, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> And indeed the World, which would otherwiſe be a <hi>Salvage Wilderneſs,</hi> is by Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment made a <hi>Terreſtrial Paradice,</hi> the Type and Repreſentation of that which is Eternal, whilſt every Man <hi>ſits under his own Vine and Figtree, gathering his own Fruit,</hi> and not reach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Hand into anothers Vineyard. Thus are Men by the <hi>Kings Power</hi> made juſt to others and themſelves; and as they may not <hi>offer vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence,</hi> ſo neither need they fear to <hi>ſuffer it;</hi> they may not diſturb their Brethrens Peace, nor
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:136912:16"/> need they be jealous of their own, no Man be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing permitted to <hi>do that which is right in his own Eyes,</hi> unleſs it be alſo agreeable to the Laws of God and the King; and the <hi>Outcries</hi> of ſuch againſt the Magiſtrates as are thus hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pily bound by them to their Good behaviour, are no more to be regarded by them than thoſe of Mad-men againſt their Phyſitians.</p>
            <p>Nor do <hi>Kings,</hi> who are <hi>Gods among Men,</hi> go out of their way in managing the Affairs of <hi>his Kingdom.</hi> For if <hi>none</hi> had Power to order <hi>Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Religion,</hi> there would be nothing but <hi>Confuſion; if any beſides the Supream Magiſtrate,</hi> nothing but <hi>Diviſion;</hi> and therefore the <hi>Jews</hi> tell us, that the <hi>Keys of the Temple</hi> were not hung at the High Prieſts Girdle, but laid every Night under <hi>Solomons Pillow,</hi> as belonging to his charge. And for as much as the <hi>King of England</hi> holds his Crown of God <hi>in Capite,</hi> to Him muſt he go, not to the <hi>Pope</hi> for his Dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions in this matter. He is to conſult <hi>Moſes and the Prophets,</hi> not <hi>Him and his Cardinals.</hi> His Sword is to be guided and reſtrained by the <hi>Laws of Heaven,</hi> and not controuled by thoſe of <hi>Rome.</hi> King <hi>James</hi> one would think had ſaid enough to make their <hi>Papal-Bulls pull in their Horns</hi> with ſhame, and to teach all <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:136912:17"/> Kings</hi> to take heed of being <hi>toſs'd by them,</hi> with whom <hi>King-Killing</hi> hath <hi>paſſed the Muſter</hi> not only of Works <hi>acceptable to God,</hi> but alſo of ſuch <hi>Meritorious Ones</hi> as may juſtly purchaſe the Crown of Martyrdom. They call the <hi>Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi> of <hi>Heretical Princes</hi> an holy and honourable Exploit, by which they ſhall merit Salvation; which though St. <hi>Paul</hi> forbid the <hi>Romans</hi> to whom he wrote under <hi>Pain of Damnation,</hi> yet, yet does the Pope of <hi>Rome</hi> and his Aſſertors en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage Subjects to, as that to which they are bound under no leſs a penalty, (<hi>Conſcientiae vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culo arctiſſimo,</hi> ſays <hi>Creſwell.</hi>) I know there are many <hi>Loyal Perſons</hi> of the Romiſh Perſwaſion, who do abhor thoſe <hi>Jeſuitical Principles and Practices;</hi> and I wiſh the <hi>Pope</hi> would be ſo <hi>just</hi> to himſelf and us, and ſo <hi>kind</hi> to them, as to call thoſe <hi>Church-men</hi> of his in queſtion, who have publickly abetted ſuch Treaſonable Conſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, and that he would publiſh his <hi>Pontifical Decree</hi> to provide for the <hi>Safety of Kings</hi> a little better than his <hi>Colledge of Jeſuits</hi> have done, and to cenſure <hi>Mariana</hi>'s and ſuch other Books as have commended <hi>Regicides,</hi> to the great ſcandal of Religion, and then <hi>his Proſelytes</hi> would have no occaſion to complain of <hi>Perſecution</hi> here in <hi>England,</hi> which the <hi>Proteſtant Religion</hi> doth no where teach.</p>
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:136912:17"/>
            <p>All <hi>Eccleſiastical Officers</hi> are but the <hi>Kings <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nder-miniſters,</hi> who being the <hi>Head of all</hi> under Chriſt, ought to have an eſpecial care of his <hi>Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy the Church,</hi> that no turbulent Papiſts or Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naticks may under pretence of Conſcience and Reformation, out-face and controul God's and his Authority, and raiſe ſuch Quarrels in the Church about Ceremonies, as may at laſt imbroil his Kingdom in the greateſt Diſorders and Exor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitancies imaginable. And indeed when Men are grown ſo hardy as to venture upon the Mouth of any <hi>Cannon</hi> which is not charg'd with <hi>Chain-ſhot,</hi> but with the <hi>Brutum Fulmen</hi> of a Flaſhy Excommunication, which doth no Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution upon their <hi>Bodies</hi> or <hi>Eſtates,</hi> it is much to be feared that they will, when they ſee their opportunity, aſſault the <hi>Power it ſelf</hi> that ſet them up, if they in whom the Execution of the Laws is intruſted, do not think fit to proportion their ſtrictneſs to the ſtubbornneſs of Grainſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, but the <hi>Rulers</hi> permit what the <hi>Rule</hi> forbids to the encouragement of diſobedience. For un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs <hi>Justice</hi> do inflict the Wrath, as well as <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience</hi> enact the Law, Impunity will breed In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolence, and Vice grow the greater by prohibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Yield them up this one <hi>Flower of the Kings Crown,</hi> and their <hi>Incroaching Fingers</hi> will be
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:136912:18"/> reaching after another; their Malice being ſo unreaſonable, that it hath been found much ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſier to <hi>deny them all,</hi> than having gratified them <hi>in part</hi> to preſcribe them a <hi>meaſure.</hi> And cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly one great cauſe why this Kingdom hath more <hi>Rebels</hi> than Murderers, more <hi>Schiſmaticks</hi> than <hi>Sodomites,</hi> more <hi>ſtubborn Nonconformiſts</hi> than High-way-men, is becauſe there is a more ſtrict execution of the Laws againſt the one, than againſt the other. Give <hi>not me</hi> therefore, but <hi>God leave,</hi> whoſe <hi>Miniſter</hi> I am here as <hi>your Honours</hi> are on <hi>the Bench,</hi> to call upon you to remember the <hi>Church of England,</hi> when you ſit down to Conſult and Judge, that her Sons may not forget <hi>your Lordſhips</hi> when they kneel down to pray; and this we beg the more earneſtly, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the <hi>unſheathing of your Swords</hi> may happily prevent the <hi>deſtroying Angels drawing his.</hi> I am not tempted to ſin againſt the <hi>Publick Character</hi> which hath been ſo deſervedly given to <hi>your Lordſhips;</hi> nor do I in the leaſt ſuſpect any <hi>active</hi> or <hi>paſſive Injuſtice</hi> in you, or that you need any encouragement of mine to act according to the Dictates of your Conſciences, and the Limits of your Commiſſions; and therefore all that I have ſaid in this matter is deſign'd to juſtifie to others the Oeconomy and Equity of your conſtant
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:136912:18"/> care and proceedings in this kind, and not only the <hi>reaſonableneſs,</hi> but the indiſpenſible <hi>neceſſity</hi> which lies upon you of performing that <hi>Great Truſt</hi> which God and the King have repoſed in you, for the Publick Good of this Church and Kingdom.</p>
            <p>But I know the <hi>touchineſs</hi> of the times in which I ſpeak to be as <hi>admirable</hi> as their <hi>contempt of Authority;</hi> and do therefore expect to be told by ſome who are conſcious to themſelves how much they have deſerved to feel the ſmart of your Cenſures in this kind; how ill it becomes a <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter of the God of Peace,</hi> whoſe Mercy is above all his Works, either <hi>to be angry</hi> my ſelf, or <hi>to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſe your Lordſhips</hi> againſt ſuch diſſenting Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, who ſometimes perhaps <hi>obey for wrath,</hi> and ſometimes alſo <hi>diſobey for Conſcience ſake;</hi> and that I ſhould rather in <hi>meekneſs instruct thoſe that oppoſe themſelves, if God peradventure will give them repentance to the acknowledgment of the Truth,</hi> than invite others to <hi>perſecute them.</hi> For ſo both the <hi>Romaniſts and Sectaries</hi> have agreed to call the <hi>Execution of the Penal Laws,</hi> and to charge them upon the <hi>Church of England,</hi> which hath no hand in the Execution of them. I thank God, I never yet was, nor ought I to be <hi>angry</hi> with any Man for <hi>not ſeeing with my Eyes,</hi> for
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:136912:19"/> not being of my Perſwaſion; nor have I ſo much heat, nor ſo little light, but that I can over-look their Miſapprehenſions with the cooleſt Indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rency imaginable, and do daily pray from the bottom of my Heart, that <hi>God would bring into the way of Truth all ſuch as have erred and are deceived.</hi> But when Men will ſet up <hi>Altar againſt Altar,</hi> and Pulpit againſt Pulpit, not only <hi>with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out,</hi> but <hi>against Authority,</hi> and make no more of <hi>Obedience</hi> and <hi>Subjection</hi> than of a <hi>Ceremony,</hi> (for which they ſeem to miſtake them) I cannot ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine how the Laws could be <hi>leſs ſevere</hi> againſt them than they are, nor how the Magiſtrate can more ſeriouſly oblige them, than by over-ruling them to that degree of Conformity which is both their Duty and Happineſs.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Church of Chriſt</hi> among us, which was once undoubtedly as <hi>ſeamleſs as his Coat,</hi> theſe <hi>Canting Deceivers</hi> have now of late ſo <hi>rent</hi> by Schiſms, ſo <hi>torn</hi> by Separations, that it is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come like <hi>Joſeph's Coat, one piece is hardly co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loured like another;</hi> and I pray God it prove not like it in another particular alſo, that it be not once more <hi>dyed Red,</hi> and imbrued in Blood again. I need not tell you what the <hi>Donatists</hi> did in <hi>Africa</hi> againſt <hi>Maximinian,</hi> nor <hi>John of Leydens</hi> Men at <hi>Munſter.</hi> The <hi>Popes of Rome,</hi>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:136912:19"/> for all their <hi>Age and Holineſs,</hi> have more than once attempted to <hi>commit a Rape</hi> upon the Crown and Church of <hi>England;</hi> and we have alſo ſmartly felt, how <hi>hard</hi> the Hearts and Hands of thoſe <hi>Tender Conſciences</hi> were, which were Nurs'd up at <hi>Geneva.</hi> The <hi>Foxes</hi> did then (as they do now) <hi>look ſeveral ways,</hi> but we find <hi>our Fields</hi> waſted, and can hardly tell, which were the greater Treſpaſſers; and God forbid that either of their <hi>Dominions</hi> ſhould ever be <hi>founded</hi> in His <hi>MAJESTIES Grace.</hi> I hope this Nation lies under no Diſloyal Temptations to a <hi>Second Holy War,</hi> becauſe we cannot yet have forgot what a <hi>vaſt Expence</hi> of Blood and Treaſure the <hi>Firſt</hi> coſt us. I doubt not but our for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Experience will Diſcipline us into an ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horrency of all thoſe <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nnatural Methods</hi> which may infer the like Cataſtrophe. It is not long ſince the <hi>Lord turned again the Captivity of our Sion;</hi> and are we already ſo <hi>ſick</hi> of our Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and ſo fond to go back, as if with the male-content <hi>Iſraelites</hi> our Delight were in <hi>Egypt,</hi> and we long'd to be Dancing after the <hi>Phrygian Muſick</hi> of Drums and Trumpets? What is it that you <hi>want</hi> to compleat your Happineſs, unleſs it be to <hi>underſtand</hi> it better, and to be more <hi>thankful</hi> for it? Will not the
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:136912:20"/> Miracle of the Kings and Churches Reſtaura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion riſe up in Judgment againſt us, if we ſo ſoon grow a weary of our Deliverance as to blaſpheme GOD and the KING, and deflower the Beauty of his Crown with <hi>Satyrical Inve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctives,</hi> and gratifie his Enemies with <hi>Libels</hi> againſt his Perſon and Government? The ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry <hi>Heathens</hi> themſelves had Divinity enough to pay Devotion to their Princes. <hi>Imperatori tanquam praeſenti &amp; corporali Deo, Fidelis eſt praeſtanda devotioo;</hi> and if our <hi>Religion</hi> do not improve our <hi>Loyalty</hi> beyond theirs, it is <hi>not from above,</hi> and we ſhall be found Rebels againſt <hi>Heaven</hi> as well as <hi>Him.</hi> For they who do not obey the King, who is a <hi>Viſible God,</hi> will never obey God, who is an <hi>Inviſible King.</hi> If therefore you deſire to approve your ſelves <hi>good Subjects and Chriſtians,</hi> invent not any <hi>Evil Stories</hi> of Him whom God hath ſet over you, falſly; <hi>believe</hi> them not eaſily, <hi>report</hi> them not diſloyally, <hi>aggravate</hi> them not ſpite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, <hi>ſcatter</hi> them not induſtriouſly, but <hi>appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend</hi> ſuch <hi>Diſloyal Thiefs,</hi> whom you take a Pillaging your Princes Good Name; the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward <hi>Receiver</hi> of any evil report, being as bad as he that brings it. And remember that <hi>Railing againſt Kings</hi> was a <hi>Capital Crime</hi> in <hi>David's</hi>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:136912:20"/> Judgment, who commanded <hi>Solomon</hi> to put<note place="margin">1 Kin. 2. 9</note> 
               <hi>Shimei</hi> to death for it.</p>
            <p>Let <hi>all your things be done with Charity;</hi> but let that Charity <hi>begin at home,</hi> and let the <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> of your Country and your <hi>Mother Church</hi> taſte the firſt fruits of it. As many as are acted by calm and <hi>peaceable Principles,</hi> have as much <hi>Liberty by Law</hi> as they can deſire, and much good it may do them. For thoſe who are other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe minded, it were an unpardonable Dimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nution of the <hi>Wiſdom</hi> and <hi>Authority</hi> of the <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Parliament</hi> to ſay they deſerv'd it. Unleſs there be five or more aſſembled together over and beſides thoſe of the ſame Houſhold where their Conventicle or Aſſembly is, the Law made <hi>Ann. 22 CAROLI Secundi,</hi> for the <hi>Prevention and Suppreſſion of Seditious Conventicles,</hi> takes no Cognizance of them; and yet ſtill they com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain of <hi>Want of Liberty.</hi> Now it cannot be a <hi>Liberty of Serving God</hi> which they want, for he hath promiſed that <hi>Whereſoever two or three are met together in his Name, he will be in the midſt of them;</hi> (and the Law allows them this, and as much more:) but it muſt be a <hi>Liberty of increaſing their Factions,</hi> till their <hi>Numbers</hi> may come to give <hi>Laws</hi> to the Government. His <hi>MAJESTY</hi> hath done nothing to <hi>impoſe
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:136912:21"/> upon their Conſciences.</hi> I wiſh I could alſo as truly ſay that <hi>they</hi> had done nothing to <hi>oppoſe his Authority:</hi> for the Benefits whereof that we may bleſs God, as becomes us, and pray the more heartily for its continuance, I ſhall deſcant in the cloſe of my Diſcourſe upon,</p>
            <p n="3">3 <hi>Our Happineſs under a Monarchical Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> which hath this preſcription and advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage <hi>above</hi> all other forms, that it carries a more evident ſtamp of <hi>Divine Inſtitution</hi> than any other, and is the more likely to <hi>avoid</hi> or put an <hi>end</hi> to all <hi>Diviſions</hi> whatſoever. For where there are <hi>many</hi> Governours, there muſt needs be Dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences; where there are <hi>few,</hi> there eaſily may be; where there is but <hi>one,</hi> there cannot, the intermediate Officers having their Subordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion either to other, and all to him, who as God ſaid to <hi>Moſes,</hi> hath <hi>need of ſuch <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nder-Officers,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Numb 11. 17.</note> 
               <hi>becauſe he is not able to bear the burden alone.</hi> We have a KING <hi>after Gods</hi> and our <hi>own Heart;</hi> may his Reign be <hi>long</hi> and <hi>proſperous:</hi> He is Gods <hi>High Steward and Miniſter;</hi> and You, <hi>My Lords,</hi> are <hi>His,</hi> from whom you derive your Authority for the puniſhment of Evil-doers, that we may <hi>lead a peaceable Life in all Godlineſs and Honesty.</hi> If therefore any have <hi>done what is right in their own Eyes,</hi> (but not
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:136912:21"/> in thoſe of the Law) I doubt not but that you will let them know, that <hi>There is a King in Iſrael,</hi> by bringing them to <hi>ſuffer</hi> what is <hi>right in yours;</hi> that <hi>whoſoever will not do the Laws of our God and the King, may have Judgment</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ezra 7. 26</note> 
               <hi>executed ſpeedily upon them, whether it be death, or to baniſhment, or to confiſcation of goods, or to impriſonment.</hi> Which <hi>benefit</hi> whilſt the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try reaps by the execution of your Truſt, (who are the Kings beſt <hi>Life-guard in times of Peace</hi>) the very <hi>feet of thoſe who bring tydings of your coming, will be beautiful on the Mountains;</hi> and your <hi>Honours</hi> will be received with the greateſt alacrity and demonſtrations of Joy imaginable, as <hi>Good Angels of God and the King;</hi> to whom we are in ſuch deep Arrears of Duty and Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legiance, that we can never pay him the Intereſt of our Obligations. <hi>Nemo Patri Patriae parem refert gratiam, etiamſi vitam impendat:</hi> No Man can be grateful enough to his Prince, though he ſacrifice his Life to his Service. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed we are <hi>blind to our own Interest,</hi> if we do not tender him as <hi>the Apple of our Eye;</hi> Submit both our <hi>Perſons</hi> and <hi>Estates</hi> to be commanded at his pleaſure; in as much as all our <hi>private Concerns</hi> are imbark'd in that <hi>Publick Bottom,</hi> whoſe Exigencies muſt be ſupplied with <hi>Men</hi>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:136912:22"/> and <hi>Money</hi> according to the <hi>Kings Diſcretion,</hi> who with the Advice and Aſſiſtance of his great <hi>Council</hi> the <hi>Parliament,</hi> is the beſt Judge of Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Neceſſity. As we are <hi>all</hi> comprehended in, ſo are we <hi>obliged</hi> to the good of the Nation, upon which whatſoever we beſtow returns to our ſelves, the King having no more than the ſerious care of a <hi>Publick Guardian</hi> to lay out our Services, and ſome part of our Eſtates for our own good, of which no Revenue remains to himſelf but care and trouble.</p>
            <p>If Men did bear true Faith and Allegiance to God and the King, and would ſtick to the plain Principles of the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> and of a <hi>Vertuous Life,</hi> their very <hi>Souls would be ſubject to the Higher Powers;</hi> and <hi>Diſobedience</hi> would be to them, as it is to God, as hateful as the <hi>Sin of Witch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craft;</hi> and contempt of Authority, though in the <hi>ſmalleſt</hi> matters, would appear to deſerve the <hi>greateſt</hi> puniſhment; and they would then take better care to <hi>ſecure their own Conſciences and the Publick Peace,</hi> than to arraign the <hi>Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of Authority,</hi> and the <hi>Juſtice of Laws</hi> at the Bar of their <hi>private Diſcretion,</hi> by the odi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Name of <hi>Perſecution,</hi> in ſo licentious a manner as they now generally do, and controul the <hi>Wiſdom of their Superiours</hi> becauſe they
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:136912:22"/> have little or none themſelves. Then would they alſo perceive how <hi>juſt and neceſſary</hi> it is, that ſince Men have not all <hi>one Reaſon</hi> in them, they ſhould at leaſt have <hi>one Power</hi> over them, to render ſuch Acts ineffectual by the due execution of Impartial Juſtice, which might be done by any to the diſturbance of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munity.</p>
            <p>When there was <hi>No King or Judge in Iſrael, Religion</hi> firſt, then <hi>all</hi> went to rack: But God having now bleſſed us with a King and his Judges, (thanks be to him) we have no need to fear the return of ſuch Diſorders; neither <hi>Micha</hi> for all his <hi>Wealth,</hi> nor <hi>Dan</hi> for all his <hi>Forces,</hi> nor <hi>Gibeah</hi> for all their <hi>Multitude,</hi> no diſcontented Perſons or Parties of what <hi>Faith</hi> or <hi>Faction</hi> ſoever, may <hi>do what is right in their own Eyes,</hi> unleſs they mean to <hi>ſuffer what is right in yours,</hi> who are as much <hi>bound in Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience</hi> to execute the Laws, as they would make us believe they were to break them. Nor will you be the worſe beloved of <hi>God,</hi> or <hi>good Men,</hi> for preſerving an opinion of your Juſtice and Severity, but be highly <hi>applauded</hi> here, and <hi>rewarded</hi> hereafter. Hereby may you pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe your ſelves <hi>our bended Knees</hi> at the Throne of Grace, for your long Lives and endleſs Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs.
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:136912:23"/> You will be <hi>feared</hi> of the Kings and your Enemies, and be <hi>beloved</hi> of his and your Friends: Your <hi>Mother Church</hi> will bleſs you, and God for you; and <hi>your Father which is in Heaven</hi> will beſtow upon you a Crown of Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Glory, ſaying, <hi>Well done good and faithful Servants, enter into the Joy of your Maſter,</hi> where you ſhall be <hi>eternally bleſſed</hi> with what we now deſire to aſcribe to the <hi>Great Judge of Heaven and Earth,</hi> all Honour, Power and Glory. AMEN.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
